So this is a secret between just the two of us.
（梨花(りか)の母）だから これからは
お母さんと梨花だけの秘密よ
いいわね？
Okay?
（梨花）あっ 熱い… 違う
This warmth!
No... this is the same feeling as Hanyuu's power...!
これは羽入(はにゅう)と同じ力の気配!?
It's my mother... My mother holds the fragment!
（梨花）お母さんなのだ
やっぱり お母さんが
カケラを宿しているのだ
Shall I let you in on a secret?
教えましょうか
Oshiemashou ka?
In return, promise me you won't tell anyone else
その代わり誰にも　言わない約束してね
Sono kawari dare ni mo iwanai yakusoku shite ne
Hold your little finger to mine and swear, lie and it's a thousand needles
指切りげんまん　嘘ついたら針千本
Yubikiri genman, uso tsuitara hari senbon
Take the convoluted story
折りたたまれたまま蠢いている物語を
Oritatamareta mama ugomeiteiru monogatari wo
spread it out and show it to me
広げて見せてよ
Hirogete misete yo
The past and the future are
過去も未来も
Kako mo mirai mo
a superscription of data
Super scription of data
Dice Killing Chapter
Episode 3
The fragment...!
（梨花）カケラは…
カケラは私の母の中にあった
It was inside of my mother!
In this world, my mother was the eighth
generation - the reincarnation of Oyashiro-sama!
この世界じゃ 母が８代目の―
オヤシロさまの
生まれ変わりだったの
I... don't know what to do...
私 どうしていいか分からない
分からない
I don't know...
（羽入）大昔のことなのです
Long ago...
ボクですら
ほとんど忘れてしまった太古の昔…
So long ago that even my memory falters upon recalling it...
Before I had come to be called Oyashiro-sama...
（羽入）まだボクがオヤシロさまと
呼ばれる前の頃の話なのです
何の話をしてるの？
What are you talking about?
When I, or rather, when Oyashiro-sama decided to become a god, my daughter - your ancestor - was very sad.
（羽入）ボクは… いえ
私が神になろうと決めた時―
私の娘 梨花のご先祖は
それをとても悲しみました
That was because she knew that I, Oyashiro-sama, had decided to become a god because I harboured great malice for this world.
私がそう決めたのは―
人の世に絶望したからだと
知っていたからです
People sinned against each other, living in disgrace.
人は罪を押しつけ合い
醜く生きていました
私は そのあまりの醜さに
絶望しました
The depths of their disgrace evoked a sense of despair within me.
Therefore, I decided to take all of
the sins of this world upon myself.
だから私は
人の世の罪のすべてを引き受け―
And thus, by having my life taken by another,
I would carry these sins with me to another world.
人に討たせることで
それらを祓(はら)う
I left the task of cleansing these sins to my daughter.
私は その討たせる役を
自分の娘に託しました
If I hadn't, she would have been ostracised as the child of a vicious god...
その役目を与えなければ
娘も やがては―
鬼神の娘と さげすまれ
人の世に絶望するであろうと思って
...and her heart would have been filled with malice, as well.
She did not desire this role, but she
understood that it was her fate to accept it.
娘は その役目を
イヤがりましたが―
自らの使命を理解し
全うしてくれました
Even so, she said to me:
でも 娘は言いました
（桜花(おうか)）
人の世の罪を 命の対価でしか
清めることができないこの世を―
If this world is one where purity can only be
attained via sacrifice, then I shall re-create it!
私が作り変えます
人々が力を合わせて協力し合い
互助の精神で助け合う―
The ideal world you envisioned, one where
everyone banded together to help each other...
母上が夢見た理想郷を 必ずや
この地に作り出してみせます！
I shall bring it to life upon this very land!
（羽入）ならば
あなたの気持ちを信じましょう
Then I shall believe in your words.
そして それがかなった時 私は
再び この地へ舞い戻りましょう
And I shall return again to this land when they are proven true.
My daughter cleansed this world's sins and
ruled the village with the powers I left to her.
（羽入）娘は私を討ち取り―
鬼神の神通力を宿して
村を統治しました
互いが信じ合い
助け合うための教義を作り上げ―
While ruling the village, she gave them guidelines as to how to conduct their affairs with regards to others,
不和の心があれば
必ずや鬼神がよみがえる―
and also inspired in them a fear of a vicious god's
wrath if they were to waver from those teachings.
祟(たた)りがあると恐れさせながら
人々を統治しました
And so, the village returned to peace. However, I was yet unable to return.
そして 村は
平和を取り戻しましたが―
私が再臨することは
ありませんでした
My disdainful power was too great to accept their world.
私が人の世を拒む力が
あまりに大きかったからです
However, this power could not last forever. My daughter knew it had its limits, also.
でも そんな力は
永遠には続かない
娘もまた その力には
限りがあることを知りました
それは 古手(ふるで)家に８代続けて
第１子が女子であった時―
If, for eight generations in a row, the Furude family gave birth to daughters first,
その奇跡がカギとなって
私が再臨すると
I could then return to this world using the "key" provided by that miracle.
あなたが
８人目として生まれた時―
And, with your birth as the eighth generation, I was
able to re-establish a point of contact with this world.
私は人の世との接点を
再び持ちました
I had intended to occupy those thousands of years with with my hatred for this world...
人の世を嫌って 私が
拒んだつもりでいた1000年は―
実は私を閉ざす罰のような
1000年でもあったのです
But they had become nothing more than a punishment.
When your mother became pregnant, I prayed
fervently that she would give birth to a daughter.
あなたの母が身ごもった時―
それが女子であってほしいと
私がどれだけ祈ったことか
I understand what you mean. I feel as if you were the first person I ever saw, instead of my mother.
（梨花）でしょうね
私が最初に見た顔は 母じゃなくて
あんただった気がするもの
（羽入）
私は 1000年ぶりの友人であり―
Since then, I have been living my life with you, my first friend in over a thousand years... and my daughter.
娘であるあなたと
人生を共にしました
Then I encountered the dead-end of Showa 58 and I sinned once more.
そして 昭和58年の
袋小路にぶつかり―
再び罪を犯しました
あなたの運命を変えるために
力を使ったことです
I sinned by using my power to alter your fate!
You're telling me that, back in the very first world,
私たちは 一番最初のあの世界で
鷹野(たかの)に腹を裂かれて死ぬ運命を―
we should've accepted that it was my fate to have my chest torn open by Takano?!
受け入れるべきだったと
言いたいの!?
I'm sure this sounds cruel to you, but that is what I have come to believe.
（羽入）梨花には残酷でしょうが
今の私にはそう思えます
I should have lived wisely with you and welcomed the end that came, whatever its form might have been.
どんなことが起こったとしても―
あなたと一緒の世界を
懸命に生き―
その最期を 形にかかわらず
歓迎すべきであったと
やめて！ あんたは自虐に酔って
心地いいかもしれないけど―
Stop this! You may derive satisfaction from
this self-flagellation, but it holds none for me!
私には不愉快だわ
I thought we decided not to accept that fate! I thought we
would fight for as long as it took to discover a better future!
あんな運命に屈服したくない
もっともっと
すばらしい人生のために―
どこまでも闘っていこうって
言って―
あなたと100年にも及ぶ旅路を
共にしたはず
Isn't that why we have travelled
together for over a hundred years?!
その果てに そんなこと
言いだすなんて―
I can't believe that you would say something like this after all we've been through!
めちゃくちゃだわ！
Rika. Let us return to the main subject.
（羽入）梨花 話を戻します
In this world, your mother is the eighth
generation descendant of Oyashiro-sama.
その世界では あなたの母が８代目
That is why I cannot enter it.
だから その世界に私は入れない
そして カケラも
その母に紛れ込んでいた
And the fragment has become stuck inside of her...
Rika, you wanted my opinion on whether to kill your mother and return to your original world or to stay in this one.
（羽入）梨花は 元の世界に
戻るために母を殺すべきか―
この世界にとどまるべきかを―
私に
意見してもらいたかったのでしょう
あっ… そうよ
Yes.
You are entrusting that decision to me.
（羽入）
あなたは私に答えを委ねている
And by entrusting it to me, you are also trying to shift the responsibility for it onto me.
答えを委ねることで その責任を
私に転嫁しようとしている
でも そんなことで選んだ人生に
価値はない
But there is no meaning to a life which is chosen for you.
あなたは
あまたの世界を渡り歩き―
As one who has voyaged to many worlds and left her footprints outside of human realms,
人の世の外側に
足跡を残した人間として―
責任ある選択をしなくてはならない
it is your duty to take responsibility for your own decision.
Do so using your own strength, not
something that is borrowed from me.
（羽入）
私に頼ることなく 自分の力で
If I were to choose to live on here, what would happen to you?
（梨花）
仮に この世界に生きることを
選んだとして―
あなたはどうなるの？
（羽入）梨花とボクの長い旅は
その世界のルールで終焉(しゅうえん)します
Our long journey will end, according to the rules of that world.
In other words, the fact that you exist in
that world and I do not will become reality.
つまり 梨花には
その世界での人生が―
そして私には―
その世界で すでに
終わってしまった事実が適用される
So you'll disappear?! Are you okay with that?!
あんたは消えてしまうって
ことじゃない！ それでいいの？
Rika, please stop using me as an excuse.
梨花 もういいかげんに―
私のことを理由に逃れるのを
やめにしませんか？
I'll aid you in your decision. Allow me to tell you what I know of that world.
梨花の選択の助けになるよう―
私の知る
その世界のことを話しましょう
What you know of this world?
この世界のこと？
Maebara
First, there is Maebara Keiichi, who taught us
again and again that our fate can be defeated.
（羽入）まず 私たちに―
運命が打ち破れることを
何度も教えてくれる前原(まえばら)圭一(けいいち)
（圭一）いってきまーす
See ya!
（羽入）彼は
この世界では転校してきません
In this world, he does not transfer to Hinamizawa.
He becomes somewhat depressed due to the stress of studying for exams,
圭一は一時期―
受験勉強のストレスから
心を病みますが―
元の世界のように―
but he never shoots a child with a toy gun as in our world.
おもちゃの鉄砲で
子供を撃つようなマネはしなかった
（教師）これがこうだろ
これは…
He grew stronger, stared down that temptation, and managed to overcome his weakness.
より心を強くして
その誘惑に耐え―
ついには心の弱みを克服します
In this world, Keiichi is now a person who can take pride in his strong will.
今の圭一は 自らに胸を張れる
強い意志を持った人間なのです
（男子生徒）いいぞー！
回れ回れー！
今の圭一は 自らに胸を張れる
強い意志を持った人間なのです
そう 圭一の罪がないわけね
だから引っ越しもしない
I see. Keiichi did not commit a sin, so he never moved to Hinamizawa.
It's the same for Ryuuguu Rena. Her parents' company didn't fail, so they didn't have to move to Ibaraki.
（羽入）竜宮(りゅうぐう)レナも
両親の会社が潰れませんから―
茨城への引っ越しはしませんでした
Her parents did not divorce and therefore, Rena did not feel responsible.
だから離婚もしないし―
それを理由に
レナが罪を感じることもない
（レナ）うーん！
（レナの父）どうだ？
How is it?
（レナ）うん！ フフッ
（レナの父）そうかあ
（羽入）園崎(そのざき)魅音(みおん)と園崎詩音(しおん)は…
Sonozaki Mion and Sonozaki Shion...
（梨花）分かってる
I know. If Satoshi is still alive, that means that they haven't sinned either, right?
悟史(さとし)が生きてるってことは
２人にも罪がないってことでしょ？
Yes. Mion lives out her days while undergoing training to be the new head of the family.
魅音は頭首の修業をしながら
日々を過ごしています
（羽入）
そして詩音も 本家の邪魔にならず
陰から支えられるよう―
Meanwhile, Shion does her best to help out from within the shadows at a faraway school, hoping not to become a hindrance.
遠方の学園で１人 頑張っています
The Houjou family does not become an enemy of the underworld and they are not ostracised.
北条(ほうじょう)家も村と敵対せず
村八分にもならない
沙都子(さとこ)にも親殺しの罪はない
Satoko does not sin by killing her parents and therefore is never afflicted with Hinamizawa Syndrome.
そのため
病気に取りつかれることもない
For both her and her family, this is an ideal world.
沙都子たち一家にとって
ここは理想の世界なの
In other words, this is everyone's perfect world, right?
（梨花）つまり この世界は―
すべての人間にとって
理想の世界ってこと？
None of the people you have been
involved with have committed any sin.
（羽入）あなたに関わる
すべての人間に罪がない
This is a beautifully pure and clean world...
それは とても純粋で透き通った
美しい世界なのです
Even Takano is without "sin". This world is untained.
あの鷹野にすら罪がない
真っ白な世界
An untainted world...
真っ白な世界？
（羽入）そうです
Yes. You have the option of choosing this world.
今の梨花は
その世界を選ぶことができます
The dice of destiny have led you to what may be a vital chance after these hundreds of years of travelling!
これは運命のサイコロが導いた―
100年の旅の果ての
貴重な機会なのかもしれません
A vital chance?
貴重な機会？
Yes, because there is also an option to return to your original world.
（羽入）
元の世界へ戻る道もあるからです
If you are to commit the ultimate sin by killing your own mother,
母殺しという
最大の罪を犯すことによって―
その罪なき楽園を
自ら追放されることを選ぶことです
you will be making the choice to be exiled from this sinless paradise of your own volition.
（梨花）羽入 あんたは
娘に討たれたって言ったわね
Hanyuu, you said that you were
killed by your own daughter, right?
Do you really think that I should repeat that action simply for the purpose of choosing my own life?
私が自分の人生を選ぶために―
母殺しを繰り返すことを
どう思うの？
If I were your mother, I would say this:
（羽入）梨花のお母さんなら
こう言うでしょう
My own life is less important than my daughter's happiness.
娘が幸せになれるなら
自分の命など惜しくないと
You can't be serious!
まさか！ あんたはどうなの？
What about you?!
あんたを討った娘の気持ちを
考えたことはある!?
Did you ever pause to consider what your daughter must have felt about killing her own mother?
It's easy enough to die, but the killer has to bear that cross for the rest of their life!
死んだほうは気楽よね
でもね 殺したほうは―
その十字架を背負って
ずっと生きていくのよ
Your descendants have borne that
cross for these past thousand years!
娘にあんたを殺させたから―
1000年もの間 あんたの子孫たちが
あんたの十字架を背負い続けた
あんたは死ぬべきじゃなかった
You shouldn't have died!
Shouldn't you have lived on and fought?!
生きて
闘うべきだったんじゃないの!?
なら 梨花！
Then, Rika! If you say that I should have continued living so that I could fight, what do you intend to do here and now?!
私は生きて闘うべきだったと
言う梨花
あなたはその世界にいる今
どうすると言うのですか
Will you accept the fact that you exist in this world and continue to live there?
その世界にいるという
現実を受け入れ―
その世界に生きることを
望みますか？
100年の果てにつかんだ
あの尊い世界を見捨てて！
And, by doing so, throw away the precious world that you finally found after those hundreds of years.
Or, perhaps you will cast aside the comforts
of this world and return to your original one,
（羽入）
それとも この世界の居心地が
どんなによくても―
それをすべて投げ捨てて
元の世界へ帰るのですか？
even if it means destroying this untainted world where everyone persists free of sin.
あなたに関わる人々が
罪から解放された―
この世界を打ち壊してでも！
んっ ハア
（羽入）私は懸命に悩み
自らの人生を選び取ったのです
I thought long and hard about the way I was deciding to live my life.
私の娘たちも懸命に悩み
自らの人生を選び取ったのです
My daughter did not make a hasty
decision regarding that matter, either.
That was our battle, and I won't allow anyone to make light of it!
それこそが 私たちの闘いでした
それを誰も
汚すことはできない！
（羽入）最後に
とても重要なことを話しますです
Finally, I have something very important to talk to you about.
This Kamunomikotonori that links us
together will soon lose its power forever.
梨花とボクをつなぐ
そのカムノミコトノリは―
もうじき その力を永遠に失います
I cannot keep on affecting this world indefinitely.
（羽入）
ボクがその世界に干渉することは
永遠にありません
それから もう１つ
Oh, and one more thing...
梨花のお母さんに
現れたカケラは―
The fragment inside of your mother will lose its power for all eternity after tomorrow's sunset.
明日の日没と同時に
その力を永遠に失います
This does not mean that it will disappear, merely that you will forever lose your opportunity to re-attain it.
失うのは消えるという意味じゃない
梨花の手で
カケラを取り戻せる機会が―
永遠に失われるという意味です
So I don't have the third option of delaying my choice.
つまり 選択を保留するという
第３の選択肢はないってことか
（羽入）いいえ 選択を逃げ
最後の時間に わざと目をつぶり―
No. You could escape, choosing to look away until the very end. Thus, you would remain in this world without making a decision.
消極的にその世界に
とどまることを選ぶこともできます
However, if you do that... Your life will be quite different from one that you could have actively chosen.
その場合は積極的に選んだ場合と
違った生き方になるでしょうが
Rika! Please don't run away!
梨花 どうか逃げないで！
No matter what your decision is, the world that you have fought to obtain will definitely be a wonderful place!
どちらの世界を
決断したとしても―
闘い抜いて選んだ世界は
必ず すばらしくなる
So, Rika, please do not to make the wrong choice by not fighting at all!
だから梨花 決して
闘わぬことで片方を選ばぬように
One cannot be satisfied by a decision one has made lightly.
悩まぬ選択肢の結果に―
人間が満足することは
絶対にないのだから！
んっ ハア
分かったわ 羽入
私 闘ってみる この選択と！
Okay, Hanyuu! I'll try to fight... with this decision!
I've come to think of my life as something I could try over and over again, thanks to your power.
私 あなたの力があったから
自分の人生を―
何度でも やり直せるものだと
勘違いしてきた
If I were to stumble, even just a little, it would be easy to just simply redo it.
何かに
ちょっとでも つまずいたら―
やり直せばいいやって
簡単に考えていた
This world has taught me how precious my life is.
この世界は そんな私に人生の
重さを教えてくれたんだと思う
I will weigh this decision carefully!
私 一生懸命悩むよ
いっぱいいっぱい悩んで―
I will think long and hard and obtain a truly wonderful world!
本当に本当に すてきな世界を
つかみ取るから！
So... thank you, Hanyuu.
だから ありがとう 羽入
Hanyuu...?
（梨花）羽入
ねえ 返事してよ
Say something...!
Hanyuu...
羽入…
Rika-chan? Rika-chan?
（看護婦）梨花ちゃん 梨花ちゃん
みぃ… ここは？
Where am I?
Just a moment. Sensei! Sensei!
（看護婦）ちょっと待って
先生！ 先生！
（ドアが開く音）
Rika-chan has regained consciousness, Sensei!
梨花ちゃんの意識が
戻りましたよ 先生！
先生…
Sensei...?
い… 入江(いりえ)
I-Irie?
Thank goodness! Oh, thank goodness!
（入江）
よかった 本当によかった！
みぃ ここは診療所ですか？
Is this the clinic?
そうです
Yes. You got into an accident and hit your head
while returning to Hinamizawa with your friends...
あなたは
お友達と雛見沢(ひなみざわ)へ帰る途中―
事故に遭って頭部を強打し
ずっと意識が戻らなかったんです
...and you've been unconscious since then.
But I'm so relieved. Your friends have been really worried about you, too.
でも よかった 本当によかった
お友達のみんなも
とても心配していたんですよ
What about... my mother?
ボクのお母さんは？
It looks like your memories are still a bit confused.
記憶がまだ混乱しているようですね
長く意識が戻らないと
よくあることです
It's not uncommon when one has been unconscious for a long time.
Is she dead?
死んでいるのですか？
Yes. Since the Watanagashi two years ago...
ええ ２年前の綿流しの日に
I'll be right back.
すぐに戻りますから
Hanyuu? Are you there?
羽入 いる？ あっ…
Hanyuu?
羽入
Oh, thank god. I feel so vulnerable when I
wake up in a new world and you're not there.
よかった 目覚めて あんたが
最初に見つからない世界は―
ほんとに心細いんだから
いつだって
梨花が目を覚ました時には―
I'm always by your side when you wake up.
このボクはいるのですよ
羽入 あの世界は… 夢だったの？
Hanyuu... was that world... a dream?
Or, was it... real?
それとも… 現実？
I'm not sure what you're talking about, Rika...
梨花が何の話をしているのか
ボクには分かりませんのです
What was that world I was in until now?
私がさっきまでいた
あの世界は何？
A dream?
夢なの？
（羽入）夢です
A dream.
んっ そう…
I see... So, it really wasn't a dream...
やっぱり夢なんかじゃなかったんだ
じゃあ 私はこの手で… 母さんを…
So, I did that... to my own mother...
Rika. Calm down.
梨花 落ち着きなさいなのです
ほら みんなが来ましたのですよ
Look. Your friends came to see you.
あっ 羽入！
Hanyuu?!
Rika?! Rikaaaaaa!
（沙都子）梨花！
（圭一）んっ ハア
梨花ー！
（圭一）ああ！ んっ
Welcome back, Rika-chan.
おかえり 梨花ちゃん
We knew that you'd come back to us.
私たちは 絶対に梨花ちゃんが
帰ってくるって信じてたよ
ああ 俺たち全員が
１つのことを信じた時―
Yeah! After all, miracles occur when we believe that they will!
絶対に奇跡が起こるんだからな
みんなね
必ず明日は目覚めるって信じて―
We came to visit you every day, always believing that you would wake up afterwards!
毎日 お見舞いに来てたんだよ
Satoshi's... not here?
悟史は来ないのですか？
にーにーは 家出しちゃったっきり
帰ってこないじゃありませんの
Nii-nii ran away from home and hasn't come back.
Rika, you're so forgetful.
梨花ったら忘れん坊さんですわね
なるほど
Ah, I see. Indeed, her memories seem to be somewhat scrambled at the moment.
確かに 多少
記憶が混乱してるみたいだね
でも 一過性で 寝ぼけて
変なこと言っちゃうのと同じだから
But it's just a temporary thing. It's the same as mumbling while you're half-asleep.
気にすることないって
監督が言ってたよ
Like the director said, there's nothing to worry about.
そうだね
That's right! I mean, you were a
sleepy-head for almost an entire month!
だって １か月近くも
ずっとお寝坊さんだったんだもんね
It feels like I was dreaming for a month...
その１か月の間
夢を見ていた気がしますです
It was a very strange world.
そこは とっても
不思議な世界だった気がします
It took place in Hinamizawa, but lots of things were different.
ここと同じ雛見沢なのですが
いろいろなところが違っていました
First, Keiichi wasn't there.
まず 圭一がいませんのです
おいおい 何だよ
俺だけ のけ者かよ！
Hey, come on! Don't just leave me out like that!
それは 圭一が―
Well, that's because it was a world where Keiichi wasn't involved in that toy gun incident.
鉄砲の事件を起こしていない
世界だからなのですよ
A world where that incident you regret so much didn't happen.
圭一が あれだけ後悔した事件が
ない世界
それだけじゃないのです
魅音もレナも―
But that's not all.
It was a world where Mion, Rena, and Satoko were all... very happy.
そして沙都子も
みんなが とても幸せな世界
Irie Clinic
And I think that the reason why I am here now is because I chose this world over that one.
そして ボクが
ここにいるということは―
その世界と この世界を
てんびんにかけ―
こっちの世界を
選んだからだと思います
That's like the two sides of the River Styx, don't you think?
それは たぶん
三途(さんず)の川のこっちと向こうだね
Sounds like a near-death experience to me.
臨死体験ってやつだと思うよ
You probably wouldn't have been able to
return if you had chosen that other world.
向こうの世界を選んでたら―
梨花ちゃんは たぶん
帰ってこれなかったね
Yeah...
そう… なのです
That sounds like a very interesting world.
それって
とっても面白そうな世界だね
Thanks for making us happy, even if it was only a dream.
ありがとう 私たちのことを―
せめて夢の中だけでも
幸せにしてくれて
でもね もし その２つの世界を
私にも選ばせてもらえるなら―
But, you know, if I were able to choose between those worlds,
私はこっちの世界を選んで
正解だと思うかな
I think that choosing this world would be the correct decision.
な… どうしてなのですか？
W-Why is that?
確かに 私にとって―
My mother's divorce was an unpleasant experience.
お母さんの離婚は
とっても悲しい出来事だった
そのせいで いろいろなことが
変わっちゃったけど―
Because of it, my life changed in many ways...
But I learned a lot from it, too.
でも そのおかげで学び取った
たくさんのこともある
だからこそ 私は
お母さんの離婚は―
That's why I can accept my mother's divorce as one of life's trials now.
人生の試練の１つだったんじゃ
ないかなあって―
今は受け入れることができるもん
人生の試練や挫折が―
Well, they do say that trials and
setbacks make you grow as a person.
人を成長させるってのは
確かにあるね
そうだな
レナの言うのは俺にも分かるぜ
Yeah. I get what Rena's saying.
That incident is the greatest regret of my life. It's something that I must never forget.
あの事件は確かに 俺にとって
生涯忘れちゃいけない痛恨の極みだ
俺は死ぬまで
反省していかなきゃならないと思う
I'll regret it until the day I die.
Even so, like Rena said, I learned many things from that incident.
でも あの事件をきっかけに―
レナが言うように
俺もたくさんのことを学んだ
あれは今日という日の
前原圭一を積み上げる―
And, today, that incident is an important cornerstone in the foundation that is Maebara Keiichi!
大切な礎の１つだと思ってる
（沙都子）
それを言ったら わたくしもですわ
I have to agree.
If Nii-nii had stuck around, I would have kept depending on him.
にーにーがいる限り
ずっと甘え続けていましたもの
But now I'm able to hold my head high and await his return!
でも 今の自分なら―
胸を張って にーにーの帰りを
待つこともできますもの
Do you really all think so?
本当に みんなそう思うのですか？
あれだけ悩み苦しんだのに
その罪がないことになっている―
All of you would truly reject the sinless, beautiful world I was so torn over?
きれいな世界を選べる選択肢を
自ら拒否すると言うのですか？
Yeah. I think this world is far more precious.
うん 私は
こっちの世界のほうが尊いと思うよ
どうしてですか？
Why do you say that?
だって この世界の
今日という未来は―
Because we fought to obtain our future in this world!
私たち全員が勝ち取ったんだもん
その世界のみんなとは
比べものにならないよ
We're nothing like the people in that other world.
Perhaps living without sin is a sin, in and of itself...
罪なく生きることは
罪なのでしょうか？
I don't think that's a sin. A flower raised in a greenhouse is still beautiful, even though it knows no adversity.
罪じゃないよ
温室で育った苦労知らずの花も
美しいと思う
だけど 風雨や暑さ寒さに耐えて
花を咲かせた野花には―
But a flower growing in the field that has braved wind, rain, cold, and heat possesses something more than just beauty.
美しさだけじゃないものが
宿るんじゃないかな
I'm talking about nothing more than that brand of preciousness.
レナは そういうものの
大切さを言ってるだけ
But if you had to choose between
growing in a greenhouse or in a field...
でも 温室で育つのと
野原で育つのを選べと言われたら…
Oh, now I understand! You've been making
a mistake from the start, Rika-chan.
あっ 分かった
そこがそもそも
梨花ちゃんの間違いなんだね
There's no point in comparing an impossible world to this one in the first place.
だって
ありえなかった未来を想像して―
それと比べるのは
何の意味もないことだよ
You're trying to think about it from the viewpoint of someone above the flower - someone greater than a human.
梨花ちゃんの話は 花より上の
人ならざる存在の目線での話だもん
Someone greater than a human?
人ならざる存在？
You'd have to be a god capable of travelling between the two worlds in order to debate which one was happier.
その２つの世界の
どちらが幸せか―
それを論じることができるのは
２つの世界を行き来できる神様だけ
でも 梨花ちゃんという人間は―
But a human like Rika-chan, while she may live in both worlds, cannot travel between them.
どちらの世界にもいるけど
行き来はできない
野花の梨花ちゃんも
温室の梨花ちゃんも―
The Rika-chan in the field and the
Rika-chan in the greenhouse both exist.
どちらも存在する
And I think that both of them are
living proudly in their own worlds.
そして どちらも その世界で
胸を張って生きてると思うよ
その時 野花が
温室で育ったなら―
It'd be wrong if the one in the field says that
it'd rather have been grown in the greenhouse.
何も苦労がなかっただろうに
なんて言う時点で―
それはもう おかしいことなの
私たちは花
We're all flowers. We do our best to grow regardless of where we take root and we all try to produce the best flower we can.
根づき芽生えた場所で
精いっぱい育って―
精いっぱいの花を咲かせる
Not even a loser would see fit to babble about how it would have been better to have been born into a rich family!
もしも自分が大金持ちの家に
生まれてたらなんて―
負け犬の寝言もいいとこですわよ
If you have time for stuff like that, you should try to find a cheap supermarket and save some money instead, you know?
そんな妄想する暇があったら
まずは安いスーパーを探して―
小銭を倹約する努力を
始めなさいませですわ
I know! I'll make it easier to understand by explaining it with a game.
そうだ 梨花ちゃんにも
分かるように―
ゲームで説明してあげるね
Hey, Mii-chan, didn't you bring some candy today?
ねえ 魅ぃちゃん
今日 あめ玉持ってきてなかった？
Yeah, I have some.
うん あるけど
はい
（レナ）ありがと
Here ya go.
Thanks.
さあ 梨花ちゃんにプレゼントだよ
All right, here's a present for you, Rika-chan!
Which hand do you think is better? Which one? Which one?
どっちの手の中身が
いいかな？ かな？
Then... I'll pick this "rock".
では こっちのグーを
選びますのです
Okay. This one, right?
はい こっちね
ンフッ
おめでとっ
Congratulations.
Here you go. Say "ah"!
はい あーんして
んっ あーん んっ んっ
How is it?
おいしい？
（梨花）おいしいのですよ にぱ～
It's great.
I'm really happy, because I picked the right choice out of the two.
２択の勝負に勝ったので
とてもうれしいのです
勝利の美酒はおいしいのですよ
It's the sweet taste of victory!
Hey, Rika-chan, why do you think you won?
ねえ 梨花ちゃん
どうして勝利なの？
ンフッ
あっ！
（沙都子）まあ！
What you're feeling right now is probably
pretty close to what you were feeling before.
今のその気持ちが―
梨花ちゃんの気持ちの正体に
近いんじゃない？
Comparing two different worlds isn't
something that we humans are able to do.
異なる世界と
比べるという時点で―
それが人の身には
過ぎたことなんだよ
It's up to the gods to fret over comparisons like that - not us.
それを比べ悩むのは神様の仕事
私たちの仕事じゃない
There's only one world for us, and things in it are set up so that we can find happiness in it.
私たちに与えられる世界は
常に１つで―
その世界で
幸せを見つけるようにできてるの
梨花ちゃんは その夢の中では―
You were a god who could go between the two worlds in your dream, and therefore, you felt like that.
２つの世界を
行き来できる神様だから―
そういう気持ちになってしまう
So, that's why you shouldn't worry about what's in the other hand.
だからね 反対の手の中なんて
気にしちゃダメなの
What was that world I was in until now?
私がさっきまでいた
あの世界は何？
A dream?
夢なの？
（羽入）夢です
A dream.
It wasn't a dream. However, now that I've made my choice, this world is reality and the other world has become a dream.
（梨花）本当は夢じゃない
でも 選んだ以上 現実はここで
向こうは もはや夢でしかない
Only a superhuman existence, capable of seeing the contents of each box, can worry about which hand will bring a better future.
２つの手の中身がもたらす未来の
どちらが得かを悩むのは―
箱の中身に干渉できる
人ならざる存在の仕事だ
I stepped half-heartedly into the world of the gods, being a mere human.
私は人の身でありながら―
中途半端に神の世界に
足を踏み入れたがために―
大切なものを いくつも
誤解してきたのではないだろうか
And thus, I have been confused
about some very important things.
ンフッ
It's time for me to give up being a witch...
（梨花）私は 魔女など
もうやめてしまわなくてはならない
I must return to being Furude Rika, rather than the witch Bernkastel...
今こそ ベルンカステルの
魔女ではなくて―
古手梨花に戻らなくては
大丈夫か？ 梨花ちゃん
Are you all right, Rika-chan?
So, in other words, I should be careful and not get into accidents!
つまり 交通事故には
気をつけようってことなのです
にぱ～
そうだな
（レナ）はぅ～ そうだよ
Yeah, that's right!
That's right! From now on, don't mess around on your bike!
もう二度と 自転車に乗ってる時は
ふざけちゃダメだよ
そうだね まったくそのとおりだわ
Yeah, that's definitely right.
そんな当たり前のことも
理解してないお子様が―
Here we have a girl who can't even get that right going around acting like she's some sort of witch.
まるで魔女気取りなんだもん
そりゃ 全然ダメなわけだわ
Nothing good will come of that!
If you were to lose your life again,
（羽入）
梨花が次に命を落とす時―
I think I could accept that fate.
ボクはその運命を
受け入れようと思いますです
Yeah. I think I'm okay with that, too.
そうね
私も それで
いいんじゃないかと思うわ
ありがとう
Thank you.
Why are you thanking me?
何に対しての ありがとうですか？
いろいろよ
Oh, for lots of reasons...
ンフッ
Good night, Rika. Sweet dreams...
Please treasure this future that you've won.
（羽入）
おやすみです 梨花 よい夢を
そして あなたが勝ち取った未来を
どうか大切に
Oh, yeah. Once I'm discharged, I think I'll visit my parents' grave.
（梨花）そうそう 退院したら
まずは両親のお墓参りに行く
I understand the meaning of having to kill my mother to return now.
（梨花）今 分かったわ
こちらの世界へ戻るなら
母を殺せという意味
Hinamizawa
I've always chosen this world...
私はこれまで
何の罪も感じずに―
...without feeling as if it were a sin to do so, and thus, I've continued to kill my mother over and over again.
この世界を選び続け
母を殺し続けてきた
You wanted to make me realise that, right?
あんたは それを私に
気づかせたかったんじゃないの？
You wanted to show me that fragment of sin that you felt within me...
あんたが
私に感じている罪の１つ―
The fact that I had stopped respecting my parents.
私が両親を
敬わなくなってしまったこと
Rika... Thank you for realizing it.
（羽入）
梨花 気づいてくれてありがとう
Stop the Dam!
Defense
Alliance
I think that the greatest sin that I felt
within you has now finally been cleansed.
ボクがあなたに感じてきた
一番の罪が―
ようやく
祓われた気がしますのですよ
Oh?
（梨花）そう
It's all right, Rika.
（羽入）大丈夫 梨花
Safety+ is Number One
You haven't stained your hands with your mother's blood.
あなたはその手を
母の血に染めてなんかいない
That was all just a dream that I gave you so that I could bully you a bit.
あれは全部―
梨花に意地悪したかった
ボクの見せた―
夢なのですから
So when you wake up, I hope you'll have forgotten all about it.
だから あなたが
その眠りから目覚めたら―
すべて忘れているように
Good night, Rika.
おやすみなさい 梨花 深く深く
Dream of how you will live your life in this future.
あなたの人生を これから
どうやって彩っていくかを―
夢見ながら
痛くないように、やさしく危めた
I gently ended , to stop the pain...
itakunai you ni, yasashiku ayameta
言葉に置き換えて、悲しみを忘れて
Changing it into mere words, I forget the sadness...
kotoba ni okikaete, kanashimi wo wasurete
あぁ、今、何を亡くしたのだろう？
But, ah, what have I now lost?
aa, ima, nani wo nakushita no darou?
罪という音の並びから　思い描かれた
Pictured by the sounds of my sins,
tsumi to iu oto no narabi kara  omoiegakareta
償うことも叶わない夢の記憶
this never-to-be-redeemed dream of a memory
tsugunau koto mo kanawanai yume no kioku
望まれたこの世界から　消えてなくなった・・・
vanished from this world that I had always longed for...
nozomareta kono sekai kara  kietenakunatta...
いつも既にかけている　人の祈り・・・
I have always been saying a human prayer...
itsumo sudeni kaketeiru  hito no inori...